<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
    which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
    please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<rfc
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      category="info"
      docName="draft-lee-randomized-macaddr-ps-00"
      ipr="trust200902"
      obsoletes=""
      updates=""
      submissionType="IETF"
      xml:lang="en"
      tocInclude="true"
      tocDepth="4"
      symRefs="true"
      sortRefs="true"
      version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.38.1 -->
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
    ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
       or pre5378Trust200902
    you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN"
    they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the
        full title is longer than 39 characters -->

   <title abbrev="Abbreviated Title">Problem Statements for MAC Address Randomization</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-lee-randomized-macaddr-ps-00"/>
    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

   <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

   <author fullname="Yiu L. Lee" initials="Y." surname="Lee">
      <organization>Comcast</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1800 Arch Street</street>
         <city>Philadelphia</city>
          <region>PA</region>
          <code>19103</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 215 286 5894</phone>
        <email>yiu_lee@comcast.com</email>
        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
     </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jason Livingood" initials="J" surname="Livingood">
       <organization>Comcast</organization>
       <address>
         <postal>
           <street>1800 Arch Street</street>
          <city>Philadelphia</city>
           <region>PA</region>
           <code>19103</code>
           <country>USA</country>
         </postal>
         <phone>+1 215 286 7407</phone>
         <email>jason_livingood@comcast.com</email>
         <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
     </author>

    <author fullname="Jason Weil" initials="J" surname="Weil">
       <organization>Charter Communications</organization>
       <address>
         <postal>
           <street/>
           <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Orlando</city>
           <region>FL</region>
           <code/>
           <country>USA</country>
         </postal>
         <email>Jason.Weil@charter.com</email>
         <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
     </author>

    <date year="2020"/>
    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill
        in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to
	 specify just the year. -->

   <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

   <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
        IETF is fine for individual submissions.
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
        which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

   <keyword>template</keyword>
    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
        files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
        output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
        keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

   <abstract>
      <t>MAC address is the Link Layer address used in the Ethrenet protocol.
        It is usually assigned by the Network Interface Card manufacturer and being used
        for forwording and receiving frame. Due to the static nature of the
        MAC address, it raises some privacy concerns and MAC address randomization
        is being implemented. This draft documents the impacts of MAC address
        randomization to existing use cases and proposes few next steps IETF may
        consider to work on.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Ethernet protocol
        is the implementation of data link layer defined in the Open Systems Interconnection model (OSI).
        Ethernet protocol is defined in IEEE 802.1 standard and MAC address is the address used in Ethernet protocol.
        MAC address is 48-bit long
        and usually defined in the hardware. Each Ethernet interface comes
        with a MAC address assigned by the manufacturer. Each device has one or more
        MAC addresses. For example, a given IoT device may only have a single WiiFi
        network interface and therefore a single MAC address. In contract, a
        laptop may have three interfaces that encompasses two wired Ethernet ports
        and a WiFi interface, and therefore will have three MAC addresses.
        MAC address is used at
        the Local-Area-Network (LAN) for frame forwarding. It is locally
        significant in the LAN and critical LAN-to-LAN
        communications.</t>

        <t>The device manufacturer typically assigns the MAC address to an interface.
        Unless the user or operating system modifies the MAC address, which is
        sometimes the case, the MAC address follows a defined format and uses 2 parts.
        Those are Manufacturer ID and Interface ID. In a typical MAC address,
        the first 3 bytes correspond to the organization that created the device,
        called the Organizationally Unique Identifier (OUI). This OUI portion
        uniquely identifies a manufacturer, vendor, or other organization, and
        is assigned by the IEEE from their IEEE Registration Authority.
        The second 3 bytes of the MAC address, the Network Interface Controller
        (NIC) portion, is an identifier assigned by the manufacturer (or whatever
        organization was assigned the OUI). Because of how MAC addresses are
        constructed, a MAC address may contain information from which an
        actor/service on a local network can infer the type and/or manufacturer
        of the device, which is useful for a variety of operational and
        troubleshooting reasons. For example, a MAC address can be used to
        determine to which device on a LAN to permit or deny access at a
        particular time of day (e.g. child's tablet may not access Internet
        after 22:00 hrs until 06:00 hrs). Such services often rely on a database
        or other method to map MAC addreses to a likely device make and model,
        such as using a commercial service from Fingerbank,
        https://fingerbank.org/about/, after which the user would then label
        the device (e.g. Jane’s iPhone).</t>

        <t>Many networks today
        use MAC address to uniquely identify a device. For example: Sticky DHCP
        assignment often maps to MAC address. In additional, many local network
        policies such as port-forwarding, DMZ setup and LAN QoS are all based on
        MAC address. There are also business policies that are making
        assumptions on MAC address. For example: Hospitality Internet service
        used in hotels, airplanes, and Community WiFi often uses MAC address to
        tie to Internet subscription.</t>

        <t>Major operating systems have implemented and deployed MAC address randomization
        to improve device and user privacy. It is common practice on many types of networks
        today to use the  MAC address as a form of device identification. This practice will
        break some applications and policies at the IP layer and Transport layer. We are interested
        in determining if there is sufficient support in the IETF community to define
        best practices and potentially a new protocol for service continuity in the
        presence of MAC address randomization.</t>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
       "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
       document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"
       format="default">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>


    <!-- This PI places the pagebreak correctly (before the section title) in the text output. -->

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Problem Statement</name>

        <t>Recently, more and more privacy concerns are related to the
        static MAC address. In particular, security community worries about
        people being able to tie the MAC address to a particular device. This
        may enable device tracking and tracing. To address the privacy concern,
        MAC address randomization is developed. MAC address randomization is a
        technique similar to IPv6 temporary IIDs defined in <xref target="RFC7217"
        format="default">RFC 7217</xref>. Devices will auto-generate the MAC
        address based on the device policy and use the random generated MAC address
        instead of the hardware based MAC address assigned by the manufacturer when
        they connect to the network. Many modern Operation Systems
        such as Apple iOS (https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT211227),
        Google Android (https://source.android.com/devices/tech/connect/wifi-mac-randomization)
        and Microsoft Windows 10 (https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/help/4027925/windows-how-and-why-to-use-random-hardware-addresses)
        are experimenting MAC addresses randomization. The randomization policy could be time based, network
        based, combination of both and more. MAC address randomization is a
        important step forward to protect user privacy. However, it will
        break some applications that make assumptions of the MAC address.</t>

        <t> In some circumstances, users may want to give the trusted network
          (e.g., home network) some predictability of the MAC address for some
          important services. For example, whitelisting MAC address for network
          access. This document defines a set of problem statements to continue
          the existing LAN services when MAC address is randomized.</t>

        <t>[PS-01] Internet Service Provider (ISP) must not make any assumption
          about the MAC address</t>
        <t>[PS-02] ISP must not make any assumption of the Randomization
            Policy</t>
        <t>[PS-03] LAN policy must not tie to a fixed MAC address</t>
        <t>[PS-04] A mechanism must be defined to securely identify a device.
          The mechanism can leverage existing protocols (e.g., EAP) or newly
          defined protocol.</t>
        <t>[PS-05] ISP and device may leverage existing protocol or define a new
          mechanism to exchange information about MAC address randomization</t>

    </section>

   <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
      <t>All drafts are required to have an IANA considerations section (see
     <xref target="RFC5226" format="default">Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</xref> for a guide). If the draft does not require IANA to do
     anything, the section contains an explicit statement that this is the
     case (as above). If there are no requirements for IANA, the section will
     be removed during conversion into an RFC by the RFC Editor.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>All drafts are required to have a security considerations section.
     See <xref target="RFC3552" format="default">RFC 3552</xref> for a guide.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

 <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

   <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
    1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
    2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
       (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

    Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
    If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
    directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
    with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
    filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3552.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226.xml" ?>
   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7217.xml" ?>
   </references>

    <section anchor="app-additional" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Additional Stuff</name>
      <t>This becomes an Appendix.</t>
    </section>
    <!-- Change Log

v00 2006-03-15  EBD   Initial version

v01 2006-04-03  EBD   Moved PI location back to position 1 -
                     v3.1 of XMLmind is better with them at this location.
v02 2007-03-07  AH    removed extraneous nested_list attribute,
                     other minor corrections
v03 2007-03-09  EBD   Added comments on null IANA sections and fixed heading capitalization.
                     Modified comments around figure to reflect non-implementation of
                     figure indent control.  Put in reference using anchor="DOMINATION".
                     Fixed up the date specification comments to reflect current truth.
v04 2007-03-09 AH     Major changes: shortened discussion of PIs,
                     added discussion of rfc include.
v05 2007-03-10 EBD    Added preamble to C program example to tell about ABNF and alternative
                     images. Removed meta-characters from comments (causes problems).

v06 2010-04-01 TT     Changed ipr attribute values to latest ones. Changed date to
                     year only, to be consistent with the comments. Updated the
                     IANA guidelines reference from the I-D to the finished RFC.
v07 2020-01-21 HL    Converted the template to use XML schema version 3.
    -->
 </back>
</rfc>
